Guide to the Papers of the United States Commission on Civil Rights, North Carolina Advisory Committee, 1949-1962
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United States Commission on Civil Rights, North Carolina Advisory Committee papers 1949-1962
United States Commission on Civil Rights. North Carolina Advisory Committee
5.2 linear feet Extent: approximately 3,900 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Durham, North Carolina 27708-0185
RL.00226
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of the North Carolina Advisory Committee to the United States Commission on Civil Rights (1949-1962), a fact-finding body, were donated to the Duke University Law School by Professor Francis Paschal in 1969. They were transferred to the University Archives in 1980, and then to the Rubenstein Library in 1983.
Historical Note
1957 Created by the Civil Rights Act of 1957
1959, Jan. First meeting
1959-1962 Conducted a series of studies in the areas of administration of justice, education, employment, housing, medical care, and voting
1959-1963 Results of Committee's work were published both by the North Carolina Committee and the federal commission
The Chairman of the committee was McNeill Smith. The other members were: Asa T. Spaulding, Paul R. Ervin, Hector McLean, Conrad O. Pearson, William Thorpe, Curtiss Todd, Marion A. Wright, Millard Barbee, R.A. Wilkins, and secretary Margaret R. Vogt.
Collection Overview
The United States Commission on Civil Rights North Carolina Advisory Committee Papers span the years 1949 to 1962, but fall chiefly in the period 1957 to 1962. They consist largely of correspondence, but also include reports, drafts of reports, minutes of meetings, and completed survey forms. Statistical charts and maps, transcripts of telephone interviews, signed affidavits, printed material which includes reports of other organizations, articles, brochures, and press releases, mailing lists, notes, and clippings are also included. The collection documents methods of data collection for social research that is directed to governmental policy change. The research particularly focuses on racial discrimination against and the civil rights of African Americans, and to a lesser extent Native Americans, in North Carolina. Most of the correspondence was generated from the office of Chairman McNeill Smith, and the collection therefore does not represent the work of other Committee members, except for their communications with Smith.
The Committee requested statistical information on African Americans and Native Americans from public libraries, high schools, lending agencies, health care facilities, employers and county boards of election. Completed questionnaire forms exist for the Public Libraries, Administration of Justice, Education, Employment, and Voting studies. Formal complaints in areas of potential study were heard and recorded at open hearings held throughout the state. More qualitative information was obtained through correspondence, meetings and telephone interviews. Transcripts of Smith's phone conversations can be found in the Education, Employment, Medical Care and Voting Series.
Correspondence in each series, including alphabetical files, pertains to the studies, background information, survey forms, data, and final reports. In many cases, completed survey forms, which exist for the Public Libraries, Administration of Justice, Education and Voting studies, are attached to correspondence. Form letters in the correspondence of the Housing and Voting Series request specific information from lending agencies and county boards of election. There are responses to questions in letter form which, in the case of the Housing Series, comprise a large portion of the correspondence. Scattered letters from North Carolinians express segregationist views and hostility to research efforts.
In every series, the major correspondence is that of McNeill Smith with researchers and Commission and Committee members. Occasionally, communications from federal commission officers appear, most notably Cornelius Cotter (Assistant Staff Director), Henry Shine, Gordon Tiffany (Staff Director), and Peter Sussman (Deputy Assistant Staff Director). These usually pertain to the development and approval of questionnaire forms and the editing and publication of reports, or provide supplementary data.
The General Series documents committee work on both national and state levels. Correspondence files contain information on the creation and organization of the committee and its work, as well as information on every study. There are letters from the federal commission concerning new projects, surveys, data, reports, and national and regional conferences. Other files contain information on the proceedings of open meetings held by the committee between 1959 and 1961.
The voting study was mandated by the Civil Rights Act of 1957. The Voting Series contains correspondence pertaining to the collection of registration statistics with regard to race in North Carolina, as well as completed survey forms from almost all of the 100 counties in North Carolina. Repeated communications from McNeill Smith to registration officials and lawyers in every county are included. The series also contains seventeen signed affidavit forms attesting to discriminatory voting practices.
Discriminatory practices in the following areas were investigated: employment of blacks in law enforcement agencies (Administration of Justice Series); employment and facilities in public libraries (General Series); enrollment in accredited high schools, illiteracy, and admission to industrial education centers (Education Series); and employment of blacks in state organizations and companies with government contracts (Employment Series). The ability of blacks to obtain federally- sponsored loans for housing and their role in urban-renewal (Housing Series); admission of blacks to health care facilities (Medical Care Series); and voter registration procedures and participation of blacks in political elections (Voting Series) were other areas of investigation.
Local experts in the fields of medicine, political science and law researched and wrote reports, and compiled statistical charts. General legal research was carried out by Dan Pollitt of the Universitiy of North Carolina Law School, some of whose work is found in the General Series. Others included: Donald Matthews of the UNC Political Science Department (Voting), John Hope II of Fisk University in Tennessee (Education), Dickson Phillips of the UNC Law School (Administration of Justice), Howard Miller of Raleigh (Industrial Education), and Dr. M. B. Bethel of Chapel Hill (Medical Care). Correspondence between committee members, primarily McNeill Smith, and these individuals is found in the General, Administration of Justice, Education, Medical Care and Voting series. Organizations involved in the committee's research included: The American Friends Service Committee, the Southern Regional Council, the North Carolina Department of Public Instruction, the UNC-Chapel Hill Institute of Government, the North Carolina Employment Security Commission, the Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, the North Carolina AFL-CIO, and the North Carolina State Board of Health.
Published reports of the committee's work are in the Public Documents and Maps Department, in the Pamphlet Collection and in the stacks of Perkins Library. Related collections in the Special Collections Department include the Asa T. Spaulding Papers and the Robert S. Rankin Papers.
Subject Headings
Civil rights -- North Carolina; Discrimination in education -- North Carolina; African Americans -- Civil rights -- North Carolina; Discrimination in housing -- North Carolina; Equality before the law -- North Carolina; Discrimination in medical care -- North Carolina; Public libraries -- North Carolina; Indians of North America -- North Carolina -- Civil rights; Action research -- North Carolina; Voter registration -- North Carolina; Race discrimination -- Law and legislation -- North Carolina; Discrimination in employment -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Social policy; Social surveys -- North Carolina; Government questionnaires -- North Carolina; United States -- Civil Rights Act of 1957; Questionnaires; Smith, McNeill (John McNeill), 1918-
Contents of Collection
THE BOXES IN THIS COLLECTION MAY CONTAIN SENSITIVE MATERIALS
- General Series, 1957-1962 and undated
  Correspondence, mostly to or from McNeill Smith, and alphabetical files. Other correspondents include Commission and Committee members, lawyers, professors, members of other organizations, and other individuals interested in Committee work. Also includes minutes, affidavit forms, reports, printed material and press releases concerning open meetings. Arranged chronologically within files.
  - Correspondence, 1957-1961, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962, Jan.-Oct., undated (Box 2)
  - Bills, statements, and travel vouchers, 1959-1962, undated (Box 2)
  - Committee members, 1959-1960, undated (Box 2)
  - County Board of Elections, 1959, undated (Box 2)
  - Fraternal Orders (Segregation), 1950, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Indians, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Legal Provisions for Segregation, Daniel H. Pollitt, UNC, undated (Box 2)
  - Meetings, 1959-1960, (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - Meetings, 1960-1961, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - Names, addresses and phone numbers (N.C. Advisory Committee), undated (Box 3)
  - 1960 Census, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Notes, 1958-1959, undated (Box 3)
  - Public Libraries (survey):
    - A-Z, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1960-1962, undated (Box 3)
  - Recreation Facilities--Segregation, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
  - Related Organizations, 1959-1961, undated (Box 3)
  - Rural Electrification Administration Seating (segregation), 1961 (Box 3)
  - Segregation (City Ordinances), 1961-1962, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1957-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Administration of Justice Series, 1960-1962 and undated
  Chiefly correspondence, mostly between McNeill Smith and Committee members. Also includes drafts of reports, transcripts of telephone conversations, clippings, notes and data.
  - Correspondence, 1960-1962, undated (Box 4)
  - Questionnaires, 1961, undated (Box 4)
  - Report, 1961-1962, undated (Box 4)
- Education Series, 1949-1962 and undated (bulk, 1957-1962).
  Chiefly correspondence, mostly to or from McNeill Smith. Also includes reports, drafts of reports, questionnaires and other data, printed material, transcripts of telephone conversations, clippings and notes. Printed material includes reports of other organizations including the Southern Regional Council, and government publications. To a lesser extent, newsletters, press releases, and serials. Arranged chronologically in correspondence and alphabetical files. Completed survey forms given to the committee by a North Carolina television station, WFMY-TV, were used as data for the literacy report.
  - Correspondence, 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: (Box 5)
    - 1961-1962, July, undated (Box 5)
    - Requests for research data from N.C. colleges, 1959, undated (Box 5)
  - Education Report: Mailings to public school superintendents, 1960-1961, undated (Box 5)
  - The One, Two and Three Teacher Schools (Report), 1961-1962, undated (Box 5)
  - Operation of Industrial Education Centers of North Carolina (Reports):
    - 1956-1962, Sept., undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Questionnaires, 1960-1961, undated (Box 5)
  - Other Reports, 1958-1960 (Box 5)
  - Public High School Enrollment in Accredited Schools (Report), 1959-1961, undated (Box 6)
  - Public School Desegregation, 1958-1962, undated (Box 6)
  - The Uneducated (Report), 1950-1961, May, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1949-1961, undated (Box 6)
- Employment Series, 1956-1962 and undated
  Chiefly correspondence, mostly to or from McNeill Smith and Marion Wright. Also includes drafts of reports, data including questionnaires and other statistics, transcripts of telephone conversations, memoranda, printed material including reports of other organizations and statements of corporate policy, reprints, and notes. Arranged chronologically within correspondence and alphabetical files.
  - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - State Agencies: Employment Practices:
    - 1959 (Box 7)
    - Reports, 1960-1962, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Subcommittee work, 1960, undated (Box 7)
  - Surveys, 1959, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1956-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
- Housing Series, 1957-1962 and undated
  Chiefly correspondence, mostly from McNeill Smith to Cornelius Cotter and other staff members. Includes a series of correspondence in 1961 from a number of lending agencies in North Carolina. Also includes reports, drafts of reports, printed material, questionnaires, reports of other organizations including the U.S. Census Bureau and the Housing and Home Finance Agency of the Urban Renewal Administration, and to a lesser extent statistical charts, clippings, notes, mailing lists and brochures. Arranged chronologically within correspondence and alphabetical files.
  - Correspondence: (Box 8)
    - 1959-1962, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Lending agencies, 1961 (Box 8)
  - Equal Protection of the Laws in Housing (Report), 1961-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Urban Renewal:
    - Printed material, 1957-1960, undated (Box 9)
    - Questionnaires, 1960-1961, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1962, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
- Medical Care Series, 1959-1961 and undated
  Correspondence, mostly between McNeill Smith, Dr. M. B. Bethel and other Committee and subcommittee members. Also includes multiple drafts of reports, reports, and to a lesser extent, transcripts of telephone conversations, minutes of meetings, a bibliography for research, subcommittee membership lists, notes, clippings and printed material. Arranged chronologically within correspondence and alphabetical files.
  - Correspondence: (Box 10)
    - 1959-1961, (3 folders) (Box 10)
    - Form letter, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Equal Protection of the Laws Concerning Medical Care in North Carolina
    - (Drafts), 1961, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Grants, 1960-1961, undated (Box 11)
  - Meeting: (April 23, 1961), 1961 (Box 11)
  - Preliminary Bibliography for research, 1961, undated (Box 11)
  - Proposal for research project, 1960-1961 (Box 11)
  - Special committee members (lists), 1960-1961, undated (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1959-1961, undated (Box 11)
- Voting Series, 1952-1962 and undated
  Chiefly correspondence, mostly to and from McNeill Smith. Many letters are addressed to chairmen of North Carolina County Boards of Election. A smaller amount of correspondence is from Cornelius Cotter, Henry Shine and Donald Matthews. Also includes reports, drafts of reports, questionnaires and other data in the form of maps, charts and tables. To a lesser extent, transcripts of telephone conversations, minutes of meetings, reports of other organizations including the U.S. Census Bureau, research notes, summaries of law cases, legal briefs, and clippings.
  - Correspondence, 1959-Feb.-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Correspondence: (Box 12)
    - 1960-1961, Oct., (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Form letters, 1959-1960 (Box 12)
  - Complaints:
    - 1959-1960, undated (Box 12)
    - Bertie Co., 1960, undated (Box 12)
    - Franklin Co., 1960-1961 (Box 12)
    - Greene Co., 1960, undated (Box 12)
  - 1960 Conference for chairmen of County Boards of Election (Chapel Hill), 1959-1961, undated (Box 12)
  - Racial Restriction in North Carolina Voting History (Report not used), 1959-1962, undated (Box 12)
  - Registration and voting statistics for 1960, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
  - Report to North Carolina Advisory Committee on Civil Rights, Donald R. Matthews, UNC, 1952-1959, undated (Box 13)
  - Reports by chairmen of the County Boards of Elections (Registration statistics), 1956-1961, undated, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Supplementary report, 1956-1961, undated (Box 13)
  - Voting and Voter Registration in North Carolina, 1960 (Report), 1956-1961 (Box 13)
  - Voting Participation in North Carolina (Report), 1959-1960 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1957-1961 (Box 13)
- Oversize Materials
  - Education Series, 1960 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
  - Housing Series, 1961 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
  - Voting Series, 1956-1959 (Opaperfolder Folder 1)
  - Housing Series, undated (Opaperfolder Folder 2)